Guide to the Van Pelt family collection 2012.005
Brooklyn Historical Society
Van Pelt family collection
1845-1941
Brooklyn Historical Society
Lassoe, Allison
2012.005
3 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes and 4 small card boxes.
The collection contains the papers, correspondence, receipts, and legal documents of the Van Pelt family, dating from 1845 to 1941. It extensively documents the estate of John V. Van Pelt and the management of the estate's real estate properties through reports, taxes, correspondence with tenants, and receipts. The collection also documents the social, civic, and business engagements of Lola de la Mesa Greenwood, Joseph Greenwood, Charles Greenwood, and other Greenwood family members.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Allison Lassoe, 2015.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Series 1. Real Estate; Series 2. Family Papers, Series 3. Calling Cards. Folders are arranged alphabetically, and calling cards were grouped into three subjects: organizational calling cards, marriage calling cards, and personal calling cards.
Biographical / Historical
The donor, Allison Lassoe, is descendended from the Greenwood and Van Pelt lines through her father, Terry Ward, grandparents Lola Monica Greenwood and John Van Pelt Lassoe, and great grandparents Lola Alvarez de la Mesa and J. William Greenwood. The daughters of John V. Van Pelt, Susan Van Pelt Spencer and Anna Cortelyou Lawrence (later Lassoe), were involved in executing the Van Pelt estate. Clyde Hale, a lawyer also prevalent in the collection that helped manage the estate, was related to the Lassoe family through marriage.
John V. Van Pelt was the supervisor the town of New Utrecht within Brooklyn, where the former Van Pelt manor was situated.
Scope and Contents
The Van Pelt family collection contains surveys, legal documents and certificates, legal notes, correspondence, receipts, bills, reports, calling cards, and pamphlets.
The first series is comprised of real estate records including legal documents, bills, correspondence, and receipts of John Greenwood and the estate and relatvies of John V. Van Pelt. The majority of the materials date from the 1920s to the 1940s, with a small amount from the mid to late 1800s. The documents provide insight into the tenants, and the structures and repairs made on individual buildings owned by the Van Pelt estate. While a small amount of papers from Joseph Greenwood are represented, the majority of the series contains information about the John V. Van Pelt estate, and the Van Pelt relatives associated with the estate. The property holdings represented in this collection include many Brooklyn neighborhoods from Bensonhurst to Williamsburgh, as well as properties in Jamaica, Queens. The locations of properties may not be immediately clear from street names.
The second series is comprised of family papers and contains two 1845 certificates given to Joseph Greenwood, 1881-1889 letters from Lola De La Mesa Greenwood to her family members, a photograph of the Old Van Pelt house, and books and pamphlets from the Crescent Club, Brooklyn Heights Seminary, Clinton Ave. Congregational Church, Fort Greene Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution, as well as two photograph cards. The collection also contains one mock up of an issue of "About Town" from July 1906, and the calling cards of Lola De La Mesa Greenwood and Charles Greenwood. The calling cards given by arts and social organizations document civic engagement in Brooklyn, representing many organizations including Plymouth Church, Clinton Ave. Congregational Church, church benefits, the Civitas Club, the Fort Greene D.A.R., and the Long Island College Hospital board.
The third series is comprised of calling cards, representing individuals, organizations, and weddings.
Real estate business |z New York (State) |z Queens County; Real estate development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Estate records; Bonds (legal records); Legal documents; Legal documents |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Records (documents); Receipts (financial records); Correspondence; Letters; Pamphlets; Clubs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Greeting cards; Visiting cards; Lassoe, Allison
- Series 1: Real Estate records, 1879-1941
  Scope and Contents
  This series is comprised of real estate records including legal documents, bills, correspondence, and receipts of John Greenwood and the estate and relatvies of John V. Van Pelt. The documents provide insight into the tenants, and the structures and repairs made on individual buildings owned by the Van Pelt estate. The property holdings represented in this collection include many Brooklyn neighborhoods from Bensonhurst to Williamsburgh, as well as properties in Jamaica, Queens. The locations of properties may not be immediately clear from street names.
  - Auction Poster for 459 Court Street (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ann Van Pelt Receipt of Land Sale, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ann Van Pelt Complaint, Summons, and Judgement in Foreclosure, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bank Report, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bond and Receipt of Payment between Joseph Greenwood and Patrick Evers, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence between Clyde Hale and Family, Josephine Wilson, 1920-1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence on Division of Assets and Estate, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Estate Report, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General Real Estate Receipts and Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jamaica Water Supply Co, Water Readings, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - John V. Van Pelt Estate Reports, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - John Van Pelt Tax Reports and Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Josephine Van Pelt Clinton Ave. and Ave. G Water and Misc. Bills, 1922-1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters from Sue and Josephine Wilson, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letter from Tenant to John Greenwood, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Notice of Auction for Lots on East 7th-13th Streets and Survey, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Notice of Judgement of Foreclosure, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Receipts and Letters of Rent Collection of Gaylord Reality Co. and the Estate of John Van Pelt, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Receipts for Holdings of Anna C. Lawrence and John Lassoe, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Receipts for Land Owned by Anna Lawrence and Susan Van Pelt Spencer, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Receipts for Payment, Bills, etc. for land owned by Anna C. Lawrence and Susan Van Pelt Spencer, 1939-1941 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Receipt for unpaid taxes for the sale of land, 1860-07 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Receipts of rent/taxes paid on land owned/mortgaged by the Estate of John V. Van Pelt, 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Susan Greenwood Surrogate's Court Settlement, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 120-125 111th Ave. Receipts, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 6024 14th Ave. Receipts and Correspondence, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 8519-21 18th Ave. Receipts and Correspondence, 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 2210 Ave. X Receipts and Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 2136 Coleman St. Receipts and Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 2164 Coleman St. Receipts and Correspondence, 1937-1941 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 250-13 Hook Creek Boulevard Receipts and Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 267 Macon St. Receipts, 1936-1940 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Matawan Township Property Receipts and Correspondence, 1933-1941 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 249 Penn St. Receipts and Correspondence, 1937-1941 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 249 Penn St. Receipts and Correspondence, 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 1815-1817 86th St. Receipts and Correspondence, 1931-1941 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 1818 86th St. Foreclosure Papers, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 138-18 250th St. Receipts and Correspondence, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series 2: Family papers, 1845-1941 (Box 3)
  The second series is comprised of family papers and contains two 1845 certificates given to Joseph Greenwood, 1881-1889 letters from Lola De La Mesa Greenwood to her family members, a photograph of the Old Van Pelt house, and books and pamphlets from the Crescent Club, Brooklyn Heights Seminary, Clinton Ave. Congregational Church, Fort Greene Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution, as well as two photograph cards. The collection also contains one mock up of an issue of "About Town" from July 1906, and the calling cards of Lola De La Mesa Greenwood and Charles Greenwood. The calling cards given by arts and social organizations document civic engagement in Brooklyn, representing many organizations including Plymouth Church, Clinton Ave. Congregational Church, church benefits, the Civitas Club, the Fort Greene Daughters of the American Revolution, and the Long Island College Hospital board.
- Series 3: Calling Cards (Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 7)
  The third series is comprised of calling cards, representing individuals, organizations, and weddings.